# 现在这道菜我还不瞒您说
I confess that this dish, for now
# 很少有人做
few people cook it.
# 豆瓣鱼
Dou ban fish.
# 汁红芡亮
Bright red color sauce.
# 这道菜也是我师父 他年轻考试的时候
This dish is also my master, he cooked it and got No.1
# 在北京也是 这个菜是状元
in his exam in Beijing when he was young.
# 我做不到我师父这个水平
I can’t cook it as well as him.
# 但是我会尽心的把这个菜还原出来
But I will do my best to restore it.
# 做不了 做不到我师父那份儿上
Can’t cook it like my master.
# 鳜鱼 这必须得铰了去
Chinese perch. This must be cut off.
# 我们原来就被扎过 扎完了手指头就肿了
We had been pricked before and the finger had swollen up.
# 对划水上边带了很多很多的粘液
There is much mucus on the fins.
# 蒸鱼也好 烧也好 特别腥
Steamed fish or fried fish is too fishy.
# 一定要把它去干净
Have to remove it to clean.
# 这鱼尾巴是什么型 就恢复什么型
The shape of the tail maintain original.
# 加工好了 你看这块有点裂了
It’s done. You see here is split.
# 人家超市都给加工好了的
The supermarket made it done.
# 没事 这难不住二伯
That’s ok. It’s not a big deal for Er bai.
# 形象有点不好 没事儿
The sharp isn’t really good, but that’s fine.
# 一字刀 斜着切就行 你看这叫便于入味
Split, slant split. You see it’s easy making flavor penetration.
# 它顺着这个整齐是不是
They are in good order.
# 有些鱼还不能剞太深
Some fish can’t be split too deep.
# 你像黄鱼剞太深了容易碎 鳜鱼没事
Like huang fish, it’s easy be unshaped if you split it too deep. Chinese perch is ok.
# 它便于入味要不然这么厚的肉
Such thick meat, have to split it to making flavor penetration,
# 它肉瓷实它烧不进去味
Its meat is too firm to make flavor penetration.
# 这鳜鱼也算是淡水鱼之首吧
Chinese perch is considered as no.1 in fresh water fish?
# 那可不是 它是吃鱼的鱼 好吃
Sure. It is the fish eat others fish. Good tasty.
# 魏刚强你看 好看吧
Wei gang qiang you see, it isn’t nice?
# 你看过去就讲究吧
You see cooking in the past is fastidious.
# 小魏给我盐 去腥 多来一点小魏
Wei gang qiang pass me the salt, it can remove gamey taste. More salt.
# 再来点没问题 多加点
Get some more, no problem. More.
# 这里边一定要扣干净
Inside has to be clean up.
# 这种东西是最腥的了
The thing has the most gamey taste.
# 咱腌它一会 五分钟
Let’s marinate it in 5 mins.
# 咱们这鱼身有一种黏液
There is a kind of mucus on the body of fish.
# 搁点盐 也是把黏液能给它洗掉的
Put some salt, could wash the mucus off.
# 因为我们腌的时间短
Because of the time that we marinate it is too short.
# 要腌的稍微盐多一点
We have to put more salt on it.
# 要说腌半小时 这鱼成咸鱼了
If we marinate it for half an hour, it will be too salty.
# 这鳜鱼和黄鱼原则上不开膛
In principle, the Chinese perch and huang fish aren’t sliced open.
# 用铁筷子从嘴 把鱼的内脏内腑
Use iron sticks from their mouths
# 给它搅出来 为什么不开膛啊
stir out the internal organs. Why don’t sliced open them?
# 这鳜鱼的鱼腹它没有那种牙签刺
The Chinese perch don’t have fishbones like toothpick in its belly.
# 它没有支撑点
There hasn’t supporting spots.
# 特别容易烧的时候容易碎
The fish is easy be unshaped while being fry.
# 趴着 撑不起来
It can’t support itself.
# 你看这水 多脏啊
You see the water is dirty.
# 腌完了必须得洗干净了
Have to wash clean it after marinated it.
# 小料呢就是葱姜蒜
The other ingredient are green onion, ginger, garlic.
# 什么叫豆瓣鱼啊
What is douban fish?
# 一定要用我们四川的郫县豆瓣酱
Must making it with sichuan doubanjiang.
# 干烧鱼是辣咸香
Dry fried fish is spicy, salty and fragrant.
# 但是豆瓣鱼就不是 辣是有的
But douban fish isn’t. It is spicy.
# 但是它后边的味道 微甜小酸 鲜嫩
But the flavor in the back is a little sweet and sour. Fresh and tender.
# 这个汁它不是说像干烧鱼
The sauce isn’t like Dry fried fish.
# 只见油不见汁
You can see oil, but not sauce.
# 这要有汁还要有芡
Douban fish has sauce and slurry.
# 这个鱼要扒下来肉 带着这汁儿
Pick a piece of meat, wrap the sauce.
# 要吃着个米饭
Eating with rice.
# 刚子你能吃一碗 见着这鱼你得吃两碗
Wei gang qiang, you normally can eat a bowl of rice, with the dish you can eat 2 bowls of rice.
# 不解气的话还可以三碗
You could eat another one, if it isn’t enough.
# 也不能太大 小葱花 这得分两次下
Small chopped green onion, these are for 2 times to put in.
# 豆瓣酱我都剁完了师父 在这儿呢
Master. Here, I already finished chop doubanjiang.
# 你这剁的还真不行 我告诉你
I tell you, this isn’t enough.
# 不够细是吧
Not enough finely.
# 这个东西要糙 小魏 那可就不好看了
If this is not finely, it’s not nice. Wei gang qiang.
# 这就必须得细
It has to be finely.
# 手艺人看哪啊
How to see a craftsman?
# 看他的精细化 看他的过程
See his elaborate, see his process.
# 所以在这过程当中 如果再粗糙的话
So, if we make it roughly in this process.
# 你说网友还能看什么
What our friends watch?
# 少搁点盐啊 小窍门
A tip, put a little salt in it.
# 炸的时候不爱粘锅 热锅凉油
It’s not easy to stick while frying. Hot wok and cold oil.
# 我们把鱼给蘸一蘸水（防崩防粘）
We make it dry (for preventing to stick and spray oil)
# 一定要处理干净了 这就蘸干净了
Has to make it clean. It’s clean now.
# 我们有时候网友会问一些
Sometimes our friends may ask about
# 什么几成热啊
what is the oil temperature?
# 一般在家里头我们这个火力还不够
Normally at home, our stove hasn’t enough heat.
# 火力不够 就要多涨一成的油温
We have to increase 10% heat.
# 半煎半炸
Half sauté half fry.
# 这鱼大点啊
The fish is a little big.
# 一点都不粘 油温必须得够
Nothing sticks. The heat of oil must high enough.
# 我出吧师父 没事儿
I take it out. Master. It’s nothing.
# 出锅了
It’s out of wok.
# 这点跟我们网友说一下
I’d like to say to our friends,
# 豆瓣鱼不能炸的太过
Don’t fry it too much.
# 千万这里边肉要保持是生的
Have to make the meat inside is raw.
# 外边定型了 里边的肉是不能熟的
Outside of the meat is shaped, inside isn’t cooked.
# 这样的豆瓣鱼才符合要求
Like this, the douban fish is what we required.
# 这是最关键的地方
That’s the most important.
# 放点底油 小点火小魏
Put a little oil in, lower heat. Wei gang qiang.
# 我们豆瓣酱 先炒
We fry doubanjiang first.
# 这火不能大 小点火 炒酥了它
Don’t use high heat, use low heat. Fry it to crispy.
# 葱姜蒜 香味出来了
Green onion, ginger, garlic. The smell is coming out.
# 这会儿该大火了 炒透了
It’s time to turn up heat. Fry it to well done.
# 花雕黄酒  烹一下 太猛了
“Huadiao” rice wine/huangjiu rice wine, fry it.
# 然后酱油可以来一点
Then add a little soy sauce.
# 醋不要太多了
Not too much vinegar.
# 行了是吧 米醋 这就可以了
Rice vinegar, that’s enough.
# 糖 再放点糖 一勺糖
Some sugar, one spoon.
# 我们把这水放点 这颜色
We put in some water. Look the color.
# 二伯一边干一边说
Er bai was cooking and explaining at same time.
# 可能有的网友没听清楚 我再给总结一下
Maybe there are some friends didn’t get it clear. I summarize it again.
# 锅放底油 煸豆瓣酱 剁好的豆瓣酱
Put oil in, fry doubanjiang, the finely chopped doubanjiang.
# 然后放切好的葱姜蒜进行煸炒
Then put in chopped Green onion, ginger, garlic in and fry.
# 炒出香味了放黄酒
Fry till the smell come out, then put huangjiu rice wine in.
# 放完酒了放酱油 放糖 水
After huangjiu rice wine, put in soy sauce, sugar and water.
# 这个颜色是浅红色的  它不是酱红色
The color is light red, not strong red.
# 颜色还是浅点 等一会我们烧一会
The color is light, wait that we stew it for a while.
# 我们烹调前加味 烹调中加味
We add flavor before frying, during frying.
# 它有一个加味过程
There is a process to add flavor.
# 不能说一下把味儿加得太足了
We can’t add flavor to strong in one time.
# 我们在老饭骨里边常说一句话
We always said it in laofangu video.
# 大火烧鱼 小火炖肉
High heat stew fish, low heat stew meat.
# 刚开始的火力稍微大一点
At the beginning turn up the heat to high.
# 这个鱼你看二伯做的很细
You see Er Bai cook it very meticulously.
# 头烧不到尾巴也烧不到
Can’t stew the head and the tail.
# 我们要不停的拿这手勺 淋烧
We have to keep drizzling it by ladle.
# 如果说我们在家里边不那么 讲究
If we cook it at home, it isn’t that fastidious.
# 切两半 方便多了
Cut it in 2 pieces, it is easy to cook.
# 我们尽量达到完美
We try our best to be perfect.
# 小魏你看颜色慢慢的（上来了）
Wei gang qiang. You see the color is become heavily.
# 豆瓣酱的香味出来了
The aroma of doubanjiang came out
# 一会儿颜色就上来
The color will become heavily in a minute
# 这个里边突出的就是豆瓣酱的香味
This highlight the aroma of doubanjiang.
# 为什么叫豆瓣鱼
Why is it called douban fish?
# 你豆瓣酱炒的不香 那味道就产生不出来
It will not have any aroma，if you don’t fry doubanjiang to the smell come out.
# 先把鱼烧一烧
Fry the fish first.
# 让它这个汁和油让它滚到一块去
To make the oil and sauce well mixed.
# 颜色就滚出来了
Then the color appears.
# 大爷这个还能搁一点糖 这叫烹调中加味
Da Ye, We can add more sugar in this. It is called adding flavor during cooking
# 再加一勺 这就差不多了
Add one more spoon. And it is almost done
# 这得烧多长时间师父
Master. How long time it stews?
# 跟蒸鱼一样 十分钟到十五分钟
10 to 15 mins, like steaming fish
# 焖上 小火 烧五分钟
Turn down the heat, covered and stew for 5 mins
# 你看这个鱼简单当中不简单
You see, it looks like easy cooking this fish, but it's actually not easy.
# 它比干烧鱼好吃在哪 有汁
Why is it more delicious than dry fried fish? It has sauce.
# 你看我们吃鱼 为什么有时候那鱼没味儿
Why do we sometimes eat fish, but it has no taste.
# 有人光吃鱼不吃汁儿
Some people only eat fish but not sauce.
# 一定要把鱼肉扒在汁儿里头
Have to put the fish in the sauce.
# 所以鱼可能淡一点
The taste of fish might be a little light.
# 那汁儿可能够味够味
But the sauce has strong taste.
# 另外我们在操作当中 只要晃晃这锅
The other thing, we shake the wok during it stewing.
# 这鱼在锅里边它动 它就不糊 省的粘底
The fish is move in the wok. To avoid the fish stick to bottom.
# 我再可以加大点火 快速成熟
I can increase the heat a little bit to cook quickly
# 观察鱼哪儿熟与不熟
To observe where it's cooked and where it isn’t.
# 你看这肉的裂纹
Look at the crack in the fish.
# 裂纹大了说明它就要快熟了
If the cracks get bigger, it means it’s almost cooked.
# 我觉得您在颜色上可以再调一调
I think you could adjust the sauce color again.
# 放点老抽 味道好极了
Add dark soy sauce, the taste is great.
# 火大点儿 开最大了这是
The heat should be turned up a little. This is the highest.
# 鱼的香味出来了 鱼好了
The aroma of the fish came out, it is ready
# 起着鱼没有这么大的家伙
There isn't a big enough plate for taking out this fish.
# 起完之后 （尾巴）得顾着
Have to pay attention to the tail.
# 别顾头不顾尾
Watch out the head also the tail
# 大火 最后了啊
With high heat, it is almost done.
# 勾芡之前我们先淋点醋
We shall add some vinegar before adding slurry.
# 烹点醋 这个醋点到为止
Add vinegar, just a little.
# 千万别多了 提香
Do not too much, for enhance aroma.
# 临出锅勾芡
Add slurry before finished.
# 葱花
Chopped green onion.
# 明油 这就行了
Add oil, that is it.
# 浇汁
Put on sauce.
# 汁红芡亮
Nice bright color sauce.
# 要是按照漂亮的 还可以搁点红油
If you want to make it more beautiful, you could add a little red oil.
# 青蒜 画龙点睛
Garlic sprout, it plays a finishing touch effect.
# 大爷先来 我先下手为强了
Da Ye have it first. I'll have it first.
# 大爷蘸点汁吃 必须得蘸点汁吃
Da Ye, have it with sauce, it must be dipped in some sauce to eat.
# 你给大爷拿一碗
You get Da Ye a bowl.
# 巨香
Super delicious!
# 我要提点意见
I would like to make a suggestion.
# 就按我这口味说 稍微再辣点
It should be more spicy according my taste
# 你白吃了一口我都没给你照上
You tasted for nothing because I did not film you just now
# 特别好吃 特别嫩
Especially delicious, very tender.
# 我来吧 谢谢大爷
Leave it to me, thank you Da Ye.
# 瞧这爷俩高兴的 真是好吃
Look how happy they are, it is really delicious
# 豆瓣鲜鱼真有那种鲜味
The fresh douban fish really has the umami taste.
# 还有豆瓣那种回味
And the aftertaste of douban.
# 这个季节吃鳜鱼是最好的季节
This is the best season to eat Chinese mandarin fish.
# 五月份 又肥又嫩
In May, it is fat and tender.
# 有网友问您
Our audience asks you that
# 怎么炒出鲜嫩的鸡蛋
how to cook a good-looking scrambled egg?
# 怎么炒好吃
How to cook it more delicious?
# 其实这鸡蛋吧
Actually, the eggs.
# 拿过来之后
When you prepare it.
# 稍微得加点水
Add a little water in it.
# 然后滴那么两滴香油和了开了
Add two drops of sesame oil， then mix them.
# 又没有鸡蛋那种腥味
This will remove gamey taste from the eggs.
# 而且炒出那鸡蛋非常鲜嫩
And the eggs will be very tender.
# 当然有人说
Of course someone would say
# 炒鸡蛋不加淀粉
Scrambled eggs don’t need add starch.
# 其实我试过一次
Actually, I tried once.
# 按传统的不加淀粉
Traditionally, starch should not be added.
# 你稍微捻这么一点
But you add a little bit.
# 打开了
Mix them.
# 确实嫩
It is very tender.
# 有一种叫水炒法
There is a cooking way called fry with water.
# 水炒法炒什么呀
It for cook what?
# 就是炒鸡蛋
For scrambled eggs.
# 像刚才二伯所说的
Just like what Er Bai said
# 加点水
Add some water.
# 捏一丢丢
Then add a little
# 淀粉
Starch.
# 然后你不管是用韭菜
And then no matter what you add, chinese chive
# 香菜
Cilantro
# 葱花
Chopped green onion
# 尖椒
Green Chili
# 甚至什么香椿等等一些辅料
Even toona sinensis and other ingredients.
# 炒出来特别鲜嫩
It's very tender cook in this way.
# 而且还有一最大的特点是什么
There is another big features is
# 就是凉了以后你试试
Taste it when it gets cold.
# 不加任何东西的鸡蛋炒完以后
Scrambled eggs with nothing added.
# 它凉了以后
When it gets cold.
# 它成了一个疙瘩它发死
It becomes like a knot and it's very hard.
# 但是还变色
Tt also changes color.
# 但是用加过的东西以后的鸡蛋
But if cook the eggs with some other ingredient.
# 颜色是黄的
The color would be yellow.
# 这问题分析得非常深刻了吧
Does the question analysis deeply?
# 特别深刻
Very deep.
# 好嘞
All right.
# 到此为止啊
We stop here.
# 下一个
Next.